Guide to the Records of the Institute of African American Affairs RG.9.8
New York University Archives
Records of the Institute of African American Affairs
1963-2020
1963-ongoing
New York University Archives
New York University. Institute of African-American Affairs
RG.9.8
102.75 Linear Feet in 43 record cartons, 32 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 3 card boxes, 2 cassette boxes, 5 flat boxes, 1 folder in shared housing, and 37 boxes without container profiles.
84.24 Gigabytes in 5,185 computer files and 28 unimaged born-digital carriers
32 Betacam
269 VHS
270 audiocassettes
61 MiniDV
4 DVCAM
153 U-matic
627 sound tape reels
3 Hi8
3 Cassettes microcassettes
2 websites in 2 archived website.
Founded in 1969, the Institute of African American Affairs (IAAA) at New York University's mission is to research, document, and celebrate the cultural and intellectual production of Africa and its diaspora in the Atlantic world and beyond with a commitment to the study of Blacks in modernity through concentrations in Pan-Africanism and Black Urban Studies. The Records of the Institute of African American Affairs date from 1963 to the early 2000s. Included in these records are conference and event materials in paper and computer files, and audiovisual recordings of these events. Events with a significant amount of material in the collection include the Black Male Conference; Black Theater Forum; the Artists and Scholars-in-Residence program; Black Genius; the Yari Yari conference for Black women writers; and the Slave Routes: The Long Memory Symposium. These records also contain material related to the files of various IAAA Directors, including Founding Director Roscoe C. Brown Jr., Edward M. Carroll, Earl S. Davis, and Manthia Diawara. Files related to the Association of Education in Journalism internship program, which was co-founded by Dr. Roscoe C. Brown Jr. can also be found in this collection. Audio recordings of the radio talk shows The Soul of Reason from the 1970s and The Urban League Presents from the 1960s, as well as May 1965 recordings of an NYU Teach-In, which was organized in protest of the Vietnam War are in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Please contact the Archives with specific questions regarding access to such records.
Individual restricted files in open series are notated in the file title (e.g., "Correspondence RESTRICTED"), physically separated, and stored in shared restricted boxes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Institute initially transferred material in 1994 to the University Archives. The June 2018 Accretion was transferred by the Institute of African American Affairs, 2018. The accession number associated with this transfer is 2018.018. The December 2018 Accretion was transferred by Jaira Placide, Associate Director, Institute of African American Affairs and Center for Black Visual Culture on July 2018. The accession number associated with this transfer is 2018.044. A further accretion of administrative records was transferred in March 2022; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2022.014.
https://nyuiaaa.org/ was selected by Janet Bunde and captured through the use of Archive-It in June 2018. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession number associated with this website is 2018.047. In July 2023, https://cbvc.nyu.edu/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2023.035.
Appraisal
The following material was separated from the collection, according to New York University's Special Collections Deaccessioning Policy.
Issues of Black Renaissance Noire
1997 Yari Yari Conference registration forms containing personal information and related files containing student information.
48 computer files pertaining to personnel issues and student-related information have been separated from the collection.
Damaged/commercial born-digital material: 33 CDs, 1 DVD, and 21 computer floppy disks. Also, a small amount of computer files containing privacy issues were removed from the records. Titles of these carriers can be found in Medialog.
Damaged, blank, or commercial audiovisual material: 27 audiocassettes, 1 Betacam tape, 2 commercial CDs, 45 vhs tapes, and 1 u-matic tape (this tape was moldy and disposed of on 10/20/2020). An inventory was created of these titles.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into five series, one of which has been further arranged into three subseries. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I. Event Files
Series II. Association for Education in Journalism
Series III. Director Files
Series IV. Audiovisual Recordings
Series IV.A.Soul of Reason Audio Recordings
Series IV.B. Events Recordings
Series IV.C. Pre-Institute Recordings
Series V. Administrative Files
Series VI. 2022 Accretions
Series VII: Archived Websites
Historical Note
The Institute of African American Affairs (IAAA) at New York University, which was initially called Institute of Afro-American Affairs, was founded in 1969 to research, document, and celebrate the cultural and intellectual production of Africa and its diaspora in the Atlantic world and beyond. The New York University Senate created the IAAA to coordinate the university-wide academic and service activities focusing on cultural programs for NYU's Black students, faculty, staff, and larger New York community.
The IAAA is affiliated and shares leadership, staff, and facilities with NYU's African Studies Program. Both organizations are committed to the study of Blacks in modernity through concentrations in Pan-Africanism and Black Urban Studies. The Institute also founded the first statewide organization of scholars in the field (The New York State Black Studies Conference) and played a pivotal role in the creation of the NYU Association of Black Faculty and Administrators.
Along with many programs, panels, and conferences, the IAAA also each year hosts Artists and Scholars-in-Residence, who during their residencies participate in seminars, offer public presentations of their work, and meet with students. Past Artists-in-Residence have included author Walter Mosley; poet and essayist Amiri Baraka; actor, playwright, and performance artist Anna Deavere Smith; poet Jayne Cortez; actor and producer Danny Glover; and Malian musician Salif Keita. Scholars-in-Residence have included Nigerian author and Nobel Laureate Wole Soyinka; and David Levering Lewis, MacArthur Fellow and Martin Luther King, Jr. Professor of History at Rutgers.
Source: IAAA 50th Anniversary Program, hhttps://wayback.archive-it.org/10560/*/https://nyuiaaa.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/IAAA-50th-8x8in-20191011-FINAL-950am-1.pdf
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures.
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The Records of the Institute of African American Affairs (IAAA) date from 1963 to the early 2000s with a large portion of the collection consisting of material related to the planning and promotion of IAAA conferences and events, in the form of paper files, computer files, and audiovisual recordings. Events with a significant amount of material in the collection include the Black Male Conference; Black Theater Forum; the Artists and Scholars-in-Residence program; Black Genius; the Yari Yari conference for Black women writers; and the Slave Routes: The Long Memory Symposium. A small amount of work files for the IAAA publication Black Renaissance Noire are in this collection, dating from 1992 to 2004.
Files created by IAAA Founding Director Roscoe C. Brown Jr., Acting Director Edward M. Carroll, Earl S. Davis, and Manthia Diawara date from the 1960s to the early 2000s. These files typically contain meeting minutes, correspondence, and research related to the IAAA. Internship program files dating from the 1970s to the 1990s in this collection relate to the Association of Education in Journalism, which was co-founded by Dr. Roscoe C. Brown Jr.
The collection also contains 266 recordings of The Soul of Reason, a radio talk show that aired between 1971 and 1986, with interviewees which included politicians, professional athletes, medical professionals, and contemporary artists. Audio recordings of another radio talk show, The Urban League Presents can also be found in this collection. These recordings date from 1963 to 1973 and cover a wide range of topics impacting the Black American community. Audio recordings in this collection from May 1965 highlight an NYU Teach-In which had been organized as a protest against the Vietnam War. Founding IAAA Director Dr. Roscoe C. Brown Jr. was a speaker at the event.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Correspondence.; Administrative records; American literature -- African American authors.; African American theater; African American athletes; Clippings (information artifacts); Authors, Puerto Rican; African Americans -- Economic conditions; Puerto Rican families -- New York (State) -- New York.; African Americans -- Politics and government; African American art; Reports.; African American college students; Audiocassettes.; Pamphlets.; Lectures.; VHS; Press releases.; Sound recordings; Black studies; African Americans -- Studying and teaching; African Americans -- Education (Higher); Association for Education in Journalism; Brown, Roscoe Conkling, Jr., 1922-; Chideya, Farai; Crouch, Stanley; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Davis, Earl S.; Davis, Thulani; Diawara, Manthia, 1953-; Elders, Joycelyn, 1933-; Glover, Danny; Greaves, William; hooks, bell, 1952-; Lee, Spike; Madhubuti, Haki R., 1942-; Malveaux, Julianne; Masekela, Hugh, 1939-2018; Mosley, Walter; Smith, Anna Deavere; Soyinka, Wole; Van Peebles, Melvin, 1932-; Weston, Randy, 1926-2018
- Series I. Events Files, 1978-1992; 8 Linear Feet in 8 containers.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material related to events hosted or organized by the Institute of African American Affairs (IAAA) dating from 1978 to 1991 including conferences, lectures, exhibition openings, book readings, and panel discussions. Files typically contain publicity material, correspondence, notes, and budgets. Events of note include the Black Scholars Lecture Series, Black History Month celebrations, Community Lecture Series, Black Male Conference, Black Theater Forum, and Caribbean Conference. See also Series III for IAAA Director office files related to events; Series IV.B for audiovisual event recordings; and Series V. for event planning files from later years.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged chronologically.
  - Black Scholars Lecture Series: "The Black Church in the '80s" Reverend Herbert Daughtry, 1978-1982; cuid15883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Emerging African Nations, 1978-1982; cuid15884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Martin Luther King Jr. Memorial Concert, 1978-1982; cuid15885 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Benin Exhibition: Images of Power -- Catalog Orders and Sales, Receipts of Payment, 1981, undated; cuid15886 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Benin Exhibition: Images of Power -- Correspondence, 1981; cuid15887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Benin Exhibition: Images of Power -- Listings, 1981; cuid15888 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Benin Exhibition: Images of Power -- Publicity, 1981; cuid15889 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Black Scholars Lecture Series: "The Labor Union Movement -- It's Importance in Developing Countries" Speaker: Lillian Roberts, 1978-1982; cuid15891 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Honorable Robert Davis, Community Lecture Series, 1978-1982; cuid15892 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Black Scholar Lecture Series: "Housing Trends in the Black Community: What Will the 80's Bring", 1978-1982; cuid15893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Black History Month Reception, 1982; cuid15894 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Black History Month Reception, 1982-02-04; cuid15895 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Community Lecture Series: Reverend Herbert Daughtry, 1982-02-23; cuid15896 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Community Lecture Series: Dr. Albert Oliver, 1982-03-16; cuid15897 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cinema Series: "Common Denominators", 1982-03-30; cuid15898 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Correspondence -- Speakers, 1982-03-30; cuid15899 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Correspondence -- Forms, 1982; cuid15900 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Correspondence -- Personalized, 1982; cuid15901 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Forms, 1982; cuid15902 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Program Operation and Logistics, 1982; cuid15903 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Public Correspondence -- Information Requests, Comments, etc., 1982; cuid15904 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Publicity, 1982; cuid15905 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Registrants Forms, Responses, and Questionnaire Responses, 1982; cuid15906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Speakers' Papers and Correspondence, 1982; cuid15907 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Topic Information, 1982; cuid15908 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Black Male Conference Part I -- Programming, Logistics, and Logistics-Operation, 1982; cuid15909 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dr. Wyatt T. Walker, 1982-04-12; cuid15910 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Martin Luther King Salute at Canaan Baptist Church, 1982-04-12; cuid15911 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Black Theatre Forum -- Correspondence to Speakers and Participants, 1982; cuid15912 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Black Theatre Forum -- Conference Expenditures, Revenues, and Pre-registration, 1982; cuid15913 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Black Theatre Forum -- Conference Forms, 1982; cuid15914 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
  - Black Theatre Forum -- Conference Funding -- Proposals and Correspondence, 1982; cuid15916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Correspondence, Lecturer and Speaker Form Letters, 1982; cuid15917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Advance Registration Forms and Responses, 1982; cuid15918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Personalized Correspondence, 1982; cuid15919 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Forms, 1982; cuid15920 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Lecturer and Speaker Responses, 1982; cuid15921 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Lecturer and Speaker Responses, Correspondence, Papers, 1982; cuid15922 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Speakers' Papers, 1982; cuid15923 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Program Operation, Logistics, and Publicity, 1982; cuid15924 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Public Correspondence, 1982; cuid15925 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Public Responses to Questionnaires, 1982; cuid15926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Registrants Forms and Responses, 1982; cuid15927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Speakers Information, 1982; cuid15928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Black Male Conference Part II -- Workshop Information, 1982; cuid15929 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Black Male Conference II -- Programs, 1982-10-21-1982-10-23 (Box 99, Folder 14)
  - Making America Work Exhibition -- Budget and Expenses, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15930 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Making America Work Exhibition -- External Correspondence, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15931 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Making America Work Exhibition -- Patents and Exhibition Images, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15932 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Making America Work Exhibition -- Chronological Files, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Making America Work Exhibition -- External Correspondence, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15934 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Making America Work Exhibition -- University / Internal Correspondence, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Making America Work Exhibition, 1983-02-03-1983-02-18; cuid15936 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blacks in the West: Professor W.L. Katz, 1983-02-04; cuid15937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Black History Month Reception: A Salute to Paul Robeson, 1983-02-07; cuid15938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Black History Month Reception: A Salute to Paul Robeson, 1982-1983; cuid15939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dennis Rahim Watson, Ben Snow -- Bobst, 1983-02-16; cuid15940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Community Lecture Series: E. Graves, 1983-02-23; cuid15941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Black Women's Conference, 1983-04-30 (Box 99, Folder 15)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- Program Operation -- Logistics, Budget, Programming, 1982; cuid15942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- Publicity, 1982; cuid15943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- "A Total Perspective" Questionnaires, 1982; cuid15944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- Related Literature and Topics, 1982; cuid15945 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- Speakers' Papers, Correspondences, Biographical Information, 1982; cuid15946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- Speaker and Possible Participant Correspondence, 1982; cuid15947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Black Theatre Forum Conference -- Speakers' Speeches, Lectures, 1982; cuid15948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Association of Black Women in Higher Education, Inc. 4th Annual Conference, 1982-05-07; cuid15949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Caribbean Conference: "Caribbean Culture and Politics: Today's Realities - Tomorrow's Directions" -- Speaker Solicitation Correspondence, 1982; cuid15950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Caribbean Conference: "Caribbean Culture and Politics: Today's Realities - Tomorrow's Directions" -- Forms, 1982; cuid15951 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Caribbean Conference: "Caribbean Culture and Politics: Today's Realities - Tomorrow's Directions" -- Call for Papers, Responses and Returned Forms, 1982; cuid15952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Caribbean Conference: "Caribbean Culture and Politics: Today's Realities - Tomorrow's Directions" -- Program Operations, 1982; cuid15953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Caribbean Conference: "Caribbean Culture and Politics: Today's Realities - Tomorrow's Directions" -- Publicity, 1982; cuid15954 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Caribbean Conference: "Caribbean Culture and Politics: Today's Realities - Tomorrow's Directions" -- Related Information, 1982; cuid15955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Community Lecture Series: Dr. Ben Jochannon, 1982-05-17; cuid15956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Community Lecture Series: Alice Childress, 1982-10-19; cuid15957 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Black Theater Forum -- Correspondence with Earl S. Davis, 1982; cuid15958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Black Theater Forum Conference -- Correspondence, 1982; cuid15959 (Box 3, Folder 22, 24)
  - Theater Mailing List, 1982-1983; cuid15960 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Association of Black Faculty and Students, 1983-1984; cuid15962 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Black History Reception, 1984; cuid15963 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Community Lecture Series II: "When and Where I Enter" -- Randall Robinson, 1983-1984; cuid15964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Catti, James, undated; cuid15965 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Cinema Presentations, 1983-1984; cuid15966 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Community Lecture Series III: Dr. Delores Cross, 1983-1984; cuid15967 (Box 3, Folder 30, Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Twelfth Annual Dr. Martin L. King Jr. Memorial Concert, 1983-1984; cuid15968 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Lecture "The IAAA at NYU" Speaker -- Earl S. Davis, 1983-1984; cuid15969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Program Schedules and Operations, 1983-1984; cuid15970 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Minority Student and Faculty Reception, 1984-10-10; cuid15971 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Community Lecture Series I: "The Black Athletes' Responsibility to the Black Community" -- Tom Sanders, 1983-1984; cuid15972 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Community Lecture Series I: "The Black Athletes' Responsibility to the Black Community" -- Cal Ramsay, 1983-1984; cuid15973 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Community Lecture Series II: "When and Where I Enter" -- Paula Giddings, 1984-11-19; cuid15974 (Box 3, Folder 37)